[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net
sc radio is brought to you by the ieee
computer society by ieee software
magazine online at computer.org software
hi this is priyanka raghavan for
software engineering radio and my guest
today is sam scott who's the cto and
co-founder of oso where the image from
linkedin and several other blogs say
we're making security easier for
developers
sam holds a phd in cryptography and he
regularly writes on authorization
and has also appeared in several
podcasts
today we're going to be talking about
how to build a consistent and global
authorization system or service and
subsequent challenges
so welcome to the show sam thanks for
having me it's good to be here is there
anything else you would like listeners
to know about yourself before we jump
into all things authorization i think
you've about covered it i mean i guess
you know one other thing is i've been
myself coding for about 10 years or so
now one big changing event for me was
when i discovered rust i'd actually kind
of resigned myself to not be a decent
programmer and i thought i'd maybe stick
in academia and research but kind of
found rust and that like unlocked a
bunch of a bunch of things for me
we're definitely going to ask you a lot
more about that soon but you know let me
just take you a little bit through sc
radio right software engineering radio
we've done a couple of episodes on
securing your apis we've done an episode
on warp 2
we also had a show on open ldap but
we've never really focused a show just
on authorization so i thought you know
we could start right from the top
where maybe the first question i'll ask
you which maybe is oft repeated but what
is the difference between say
authentication and authorization can you
define the terms plus it's a great
question especially because a lot of the
time people just say auth and they sort
of maybe meet either one so it's good to
clarify
so authentication is the process you go
through of identifying who somebody is
you know so typically this means you log
in with username and password or you
maybe log in with a maybe like a social
login facebook or google it's kind of
that process through which you know the
website identifies who you are on the
other hand so authorization is kind of
the bit that comes next it's like now
that i know who you are what are you
allowed to do
those are kind of the two pieces and
what gets really challenging here as
well you just touched on a few
technologies like oh what's on ldap
where
it starts blurring the lines between the
two a lot i mean you know oauth is
technically primarily around
authorization in a sort of a different
context it's granting consent to other
people to access your data on your
behalf
also use sometimes for doing
authentication like you know can i check
you have this identity and the two terms
get very very mixed and very
interchangeable
okay so maybe then you can break it down
another terminology which is often seen
in literature is our back
what is that can you define that yes
rbac stands for role-based access
control it's a pretty broad term
it captures the sort of the idea that
you know instead of just saying directly
like what can a user do you sort of
group a bunch of users together under
like a you know a role is what it's
called you basically define what that
role can do instead
and so you imagine you have a website
with like millions of users you maybe
just can sort of segment them into two
different user types you have members
and admins those might be the two
different roles and then it's like
pretty easy to say members can do xyz
admins can do abc and so it's kind of a
way of structuring that authorization
logic you said you have a group i guess
a group of individuals who belong to a
particular role and then you can give
them what can they do like i guess on a
resource i guess would that be right
exactly yes so another thing that i see
is especially when i was researching
before talking to you was there was
another term called reback which is
relationship based authorization so can
you also define that
yeah so in some ways you can think of
relationship based access control reback
as a more general version of role based
so instead of just saying
you know grouping users by a role you
start saying well like what other kinds
of relationships exist between things
maybe users and resources of resources
and other resources
a simple one might be
most websites you know if you post a
comment or something you can normally
also delete that comment or maybe even
edit that comment you know but most
users can't
and so it's kind of saying well you have
a you have a relationship with that
comment you're the one who submitted the
comment and as the submitter you're able
to you know make certain changes and
it's kind of like different versions of
that so maybe you have a good example
would be like in a google drive like
system you have you know files belong to
folders folders along to other folders
folders belong to organizations like all
of those are the relationships between
the data and there's kind of different
forms of relationships there it's like
you know maybe it's a user to a resource
you know you create a document it's a
resource to another resource you know
document belongs to a folder you maybe
throw a role in there as well and it's
you know you're a an admin of a folder
and the document belongs to the folder
you can do certain things
i think this kind of separation between
the two is a relatively new thing like a
lot of what i've just described could
also sort of be broadly captured in the
our back in the role based paradigm like
it'll sound similar like oh i'm in i'm
an admin of the folder and the documents
in the folder like sounds very rosy but
i think kind of go to actually a little
bit of granularity and saying well
actually we're describing something
unique here by describing this like file
system hierarchy is is what reebok's
about
great another
term to add to this picture is the
authorization model
where whenever i read a lot of articles
or papers they talk about how important
it is to have a good authorization model
to enforce things so can you maybe
define that so all of this do you put
that into an authorization model yeah
absolutely so the way i kind of think
about it is to start with
the way i described authorization is is
this entirely open-ended question who
can do what it's like okay like where'd
i begin so the idea of authorization
models is really just sort of
identifying patterns that are very very
common
out there and sort of giving you a
little bit more structure on how you go
about answering that question
and so
really what it allows you to do is sort
of say like you know if your app fits
this kind of a shape like if you are
building a b2b app you will probably
want to use role-based system like very
very commonly you know and you know you
should think about it as users have a
role inside an organization and they can
do these things
you sort of take in this problem which
is entirely open-ended completely open
to someone to solve however they want to
into something which is like now has
existing paths existing templates and
like give someone a little more
structure to approach it and that's kind
of what a model is about
so once you have a model i guess it
becomes easier to make decisions or
enforce
policies or would i be right and saying
that you've touched on a few things like
you can kind of break up how you go
about implementing authorization into a
few different pieces so the way we talk
about it is
there's kind of a separation between
enforcement and decisions
enforcement it's the lines of code you
add inside your app that kind of
ultimately
do you show a page to a user or you
redirect them to an error page that's
kind of like the enforcement piece like
what do you do once you know if a user
can is allowed to do something or not
the decision piece is like how do you
make the decision if they should or not
so like how do i answer the question is
this user allowed to see this page or
this document when we talk about that
kind of like decision mechanism that's
really where those authorization models
come in it's like
how do i go about answering that
question like what am i trying to get to
the policy piece that you touched on
plays into
kind of the specifics of how you
actually implement that decision
mechanism like you might say okay i want
roles
how do you want to implement that you
could you know use a roles library you
could use a policy engine it's kind of
multiple different approaches i think i
understood that it's very important to
make that distinction okay that's great
so let's now that we've got the
definitions out of the way or maybe you
can do a little deep dive into
say one of the main parts of this
podcast which is also about the google
zanzibar system which i think we'll jump
into but before that you know we had the
traditional way of doing authorization
was you know say with ldap where you
have a group of users belonging to one
particular part of the org and then they
are given access to a resource how does
that differ from say what i don't know
if the right term is to call it new age
authorization or maybe it's been around
for a long time but new age services
that focus on doing authorization house
how is it different that's a great
question and in some ways it kind of
comes back to
what i'm saying earlier you know
authorization it kind of does cover a
lot of different topics
i think what we've seen has changed
yeah in the last i know several decades
really is there's been a huge shift from
a lot of software development being done
like in-house internally inside
organizations a lot of it being really
an internal thing into you know the
explosion of like software as a service
and people building software products
and that's kind of the
shift of authorization models like so
you know things like ldap active
directory those kind of technologies
you know it's an interface
for
managing and assigning users to
permissions to groups to roles things
like that the focus is on like you know
i have a set of users
how do i you know give them the right
permissions how do i
group them together assign them to
resources things like that which makes
sense for like in an
internal it team inside enterprise
needs to give the sales team access to
the sales folder with the sales reports
things like that when we talk about the
kind of new authorization systems
we're talking about a different
different set of people we're talking
about you know developers building
applications for
their end users
those are now like multiple
organizations not just one organization
and so in some ways
you know what we're talking about is how
how do people build things like ldap
into their apps you know so ldap is kind
of it's an existing product that's you
know integrated with different systems
but now it's like well you're building
your own app how do you want
authorization how do you want users to
like manage things inside your
application so if someone enrolls you
create a new organization and they want
to add people to groups like what's
their experience
and ldap wasn't really
designed to be used in that way that
it'd be like embedded in other products
and
in other ways is you know not the
easiest thing to use so it's not like
something that people have like jumped
to try and integrate into their
applications
true
we can now jump into a little bit into
the google zanzibar project and i think
in the show notes of this podcast i will
add a link to the paper that came out
from google there were several things
that stood out in the paper but maybe we
can take it like you know one by one
the first thing what i wanted to ask you
was maybe you could tell us a little bit
about the zanzibar system before you
know we jump into a few things
can you just talk a little bit about
that sure so google zanzibar is the name
of a system developed at google they
released a paper on this in about 2019 i
think it was
it's the central system for how google
does authorization across like their
entire
fleet of applications so you know
everything from you know google drive
and google documents to you know youtube
for example
and
it's a phenomenal piece of engineering
there's two pieces that i love to call
out as like the real like core
innovations
i mean one is like the sort of the mind
mind-blowing scale that um
needs to that needs to happen for google
to do authorization at google for all
those services right
but i think the second one it touches on
what we're speaking about earlier it's
as far as i'm aware it's kind of one of
the first
kind of really publicly spoken about
implementations of relationship-based
access control i think people spoke
about it in the context of
like social graphs like facebook
previously but i hadn't seen anyone
who'd written about it in quite such a
sort of b2b focus oriented way like they
had at google so it's kind of those
really like those two core pieces like
the model that they spoke about and they
shared and like how developers of google
build apps
with the system
and then there's just like the feats of
engineering to make this thing
scale
so i think they refer to something
called as a relationship tuple and
nothing was another thing called name
space configuration
being from a mathematical background i'm
sure you uh understood that piece where
there's a lot of scary equations uh but
i think essentially it was describing
the relationship tuple as well as
i think how they grouped that under a
namespace maybe you could just give us a
little intro to that
yes i have a background in in academia
but i had to read that paper numerous
times until it finally kind of fell into
place
it's not a light concept
it's a really interesting system so i
mean to start with the problem is
solving we spoke about reback
relationship based access control
earlier and i said you know it's like a
file belongs to a folder a user has a
role for a folder a document is inside a
folder you know things like that a lot
of that is an important step there is
the data
who has what role for what and what
folders this file belong to and things
like that
and these are very
varied data sources that can
look completely different they can be
stored and managed in multiple different
ways
so if you want to start thinking about
how do we write a like consistent
abstraction over all these kind of
things
you have a really hard problem in your
hands
because you now have like i know 500
different teams across google running
different applications for different
purposes using different back-ends and
stuff all these kinds of things
and you're trying to say well actually
no i want to be able to say that there
is like one single way of doing
authorization there's one consistent way
of doing authorization
and so the way that google went about
solving this
is they basically first came up with a
kind of unified data format and that's
those relationship two ports
they basically said we're gonna have a
storage engine for that data
and this is gonna be the format it's
basically gonna be consists of three
things
the subject the predicate and the
objects so the subject would be like the
you know say the user
the predicate would be like you know the
admin role and the object would be a
folder because like pretty much all
relationships you can kind of kind of
think of them like a graph you know
there's like sort of draw a line between
a user and that folder and the like the
value on the on the edge would be like
the admin role or something or you know
file to a folder and that folder is like
the parent or something
and so they kind of said well we just
can take all that data and you just need
to like send that data to us and put it
into this format
and now what we have is just like one
data store that has all these different
data formats in one consistent way
now that we have it in this format like
we can
basically build an authorization system
on top of it and that's kind of where
the namespace configuration piece comes
in it's basically a
configuration format for developers to
like tell
this central system kind of telling them
like what does this data mean and like
how do you combine it and like compose
it together
so
you know the kind of thing you might say
is
if you're an admin of a folder then
you're an admin of any file inside that
folder
and so the configuration format kind of
allows you to express that kind of logic
here's how you kind of take those data
pieces and kind of combine them together
putting all that stuff together you now
have like the core of this authorization
system it's not fully the way to
authorization but it's like a long way
there it's like what relationship do i
have with this piece of data
this authorization engine can basically
take the configuration can take all of
its data and do that expensive
computation like you know recursively
this file belongs to this folder this
folder wants this folder this folder
launched this organization oh and this
user is an admin of that organization so
tracing all that through you know doing
that recursive query i can figure out
that like yes you are an owner of this
file and voila your google document
opens and you know you're allowed to go
and edit it
the other part uh where you know that
google document opening quickly uh is
also a big thing i think the thing that
fantastically stood out in that paper
was of course the scalability challenges
and the numbers that they threw out
there right like just to quote a few of
it i have to read it from here one i
think it said something like 1500
namespace which is defined by hundreds
of clients and there were two trillion
relationship tuples of about 100
terabytes and he was able to handle 10
million client queries per second
so
in this regard i wanted to ask you your
take on how important is it for a good
authorization system to place importance
on say scalability and consistency i
mean those numbers kind of speak for
themselves right i mean if you think
about the
the volume of data is not surprising
when i just you know spoke about what it
consists of files blowing to folders
users having wrote like a lot of that is
really core application data and so
you're saying
you know this is a central data store
that is handling
a big chunk of
google's data you know and that's why
there is 10 trillion whatever it was
relationships that's you know data
basically collected from every app at
google
and then you you think about the you
know 10 million queries per second
authorization is something that is
happening on
or should be happening either once if
not multiple times on like every single
request that goes to any application
like anytime a user reads a piece of
data you should be checking are they
allowed to read that anytime they try
and do something you need to be checking
are they allowed to do that for any
application authorization is always
going to be this piece that is
effectively
kind of like kind of a fixed cost on
the scale of your application it's like
not something that just
you know it's painful at a certain stage
it's like no it's always going to be
it's always getting expensive
and it's pretty common basically for any
for any team that like authorization is
going to be this like hugely impactful
performing piece of their their app and
i think you know basically what google
did by putting this all into one place
and being able to measure is you can
kind of see the impact of that full
disclosure here so at my day job i also
have been working on building a kind of
unified authorization service we're on
iteration 2 right now it's tough trying
to build something generically is
challenging to say the least so in your
experience should you build your own
authorization service or should you
repurpose something
any advice on that
the challenge is there really
aren't that many existing solutions out
there i mean that's obviously so that
we're trying to change you know we're
trying to address by building building
stuff and and there's kind of a few
other
people out there trying to do the same
the challenge a lot of people face that
we've spoken we've spoken with is
companies rather share like 80 of like
kind of the same logic the same core
pieces and and that stuff you could
maybe try and like standardize or you
could build like one product for and
solve but everybody has their own like
20 of like special unique to their
business things they need to handle
you know whether it's like
some
billing based logic where if you've paid
for a certainty you get access maybe
it's around like usage quotas maybe it's
around i know you have a specific like
collaboration and sharing model like
everyone has these unique pieces and so
it can be really hard to find something
like off the shelf that like just works
you know you take something like like a
zanzibar as i say earlier it gets you
like a lot of the way there if it
doesn't actually even like fully solve
your problem i think the key key problem
that like google science bar solves is
performing data lookups over like very
relational data very like hierarchical
nested data especially if you want to do
that across
like multiple applications it's like one
of the things that zanzibar was needed
to solve was like
i might get the specifics wrong of this
but it's like if you're embedding a
youtube video inside a google document
then you might still need to do
authorization on the youtube document
and the google document and like kind of
do those things together it's like get
kind of like messy nested but that's
like one one big piece that zanzibar is
going after but it doesn't kind of
actually help you go do that like final
piece of
what different permissions do you have
inside a google document and like what
can what kind of editor or document do
versus what kind of viewer can do and
like what should the user interface look
like like what pieces of data should we
share to the user like should we tell
the user if they can do this or not the
challenge with authorization is there
like so many different parts of the
prompt to solve that cut across so many
different parts of the stack
that it's sort of hard to talk about
like
do we build an authorization service or
not like
should someone solve this or not it's
around finding the
suitable pieces to
attack like the different parts of the
problem you have
zanzibar i think specifically is very
good at solving that like scaling
authorization
for deeply hierarchical nested data like
a global scale
but it's also not like a template to
build something and solve all your
problems
what i'm hearing is there's just not any
one magic bullet for your authorization
challenges oh yeah unfortunately
you have to go through the hard task of
actually building the relationships and
trying to work it out i guess the
modeling is super important before you
jump into any implementation
and enforcement
so now i guess i should move on to the
meat of what we're here to talk with you
about which is also what is also i did
read on twitter that also means there in
spanish what's the inspiration and how
did that tie in with authorization yeah
i was always indeed fair in spanish the
name came about
i mean honestly because as you mentioned
at the very beginning right like
what we're about as a company is is
making security easier for developers
and
when graham and i and my co-founder and
i were like coming up with names i kind
of had like one requirement i was like i
don't want to be named like all those
other security companies that sound
scary and intimidating and they always
have like some security name in them or
fortress or things like that and just
they really kind of want to feel like
they're selling you on like this you
know where the secure solution needs to
be scared and trust us like that's not
what we're about we're about like making
security more accessible for developers
empowering them giving them tools that
help them
like take away the bits they don't want
to solve and kind of make it easier for
them to build and so that was my
requirement that we had something that
was kind of a little bit more friendly
and accessible
it happens the graham and i both speak
spanish and so and we just and we wanted
something that was like kind of easy to
remember and easy to spell and randomly
came up with with oso just kind of fell
in love with that
okay so what can also do
yeah so oso is an open source framework
for authorization and the kind of core
of it is helping you figure out how to
build authorization into your
application a few core pieces of this
we've touched on a lot so far but so we
have for example a party language called
polar that has a lot of like kind of
building blocks and built-in pieces to
help you with that modeling piece so for
things like roles and relationships that
we've touched on we have like specific
patterns built into that to like help
you get started and to say like
here's the backbone of your
authorization model here is you know
that 80 that you should just kind of do
because the best practice and like kind
of you know will give you that piece the
policy language piece of it means it's
like super flexible to do all those kind
of like
extra
custom things you're gonna need to do
you know you can you know if this thing
is public you can see it and if the you
know whatever this was created in the
last 10 days and you can't edit it you
know whatever the custom logic needs to
be like the policy engine can help you
do
and so that's like on the modeling front
we support like a number of different
languages and we have a kind of a bunch
of enforcement apis that really helps
you with the
how do you actually make an integrated
authorization like into your application
like how do you make sure you're turning
the right pieces of data how can you you
know make sure you're taking the right
action at the right time and kind of
making sure you don't get anything wrong
so you talked about patterns what is
that can we just explain that a little
bit more what do you mean that patterns
so we have this concept of a resource
block the policies you write with also
very resource-centric because a lot of
authorization tends to be like can i see
this thing or not and so we have
you know syntax built into language to
express hey i have a resource
these are the kinds of permissions that
users can have on that resource you know
they can read they can write they can
delete here are the roles that i want to
exist on this resource and like hear the
relationships that this resource has
with other ones you know so
you know i have a document and it has a
parent folder and so we kind of have
like syntax that helps you like specify
that like declare his here's everything
i know about my resource now that you
have kind of like that piece in place
we make it like super easy to to write
your authorization logic from that you
know user can read this document if they
are an admin of the parent folder
like you literally just write you know
read if admin on parent that's simple to
write that model so we kind of give you
those like building blocks there so you
can kind of get your core authorization
model built out really quickly so
there's a lot of examples and things
like that to start off lots of darks
lots of examples lots of like yeah
sample applications using this things
like that one of the things that you
talked about when you were chatting
right now is you know you need to do
authorization at like say every level
like it could be
right from the ui to the business logic
to maybe at the database
so does also do give you like patterns
for that as well like yeah that's coming
coming back to the the enforcement apis
i was talking about it just kind of
provides some more context for folks
listening in something i think people
often overlook with authorization is
just like how far it can spread through
an app authorization done really well
can be like should be bubbled up like
all the way to the user interface so
you're going through the website you're
trying to do something and maybe the
button is grayed out and you hover over
and says like you know only admins can
delete this
that right there is like your
authorization logic that's been like
presented all the way up to your user i
think the worst people have seen of this
is you try and do something and you get
some like horrible pop-up you can't do
this talk to your administrator
like what
this becomes like a really interesting
challenge with authorizations it's like
you want to apply best practices and
like decouple it and keep it separate
from your business logic but it it's so
pervasive how do you solve that the way
we let you do that with oso so you
express your logic in this party
language and that's kind of it's by
itself kind of separate from the app but
when you need to
integrate with your applications we have
like different apis of different layers
so
one that's useful for the for like the
front end is you can get you can ask
also for like a list of all the things
the user can do
and then you can like return that's the
front end and use it to like make ui
differences
the core one is basically just
authorizing can you use to do this thing
or not but then we also have you know
things like an authorized query api
which basically allows you to
get your policy your authorization logic
utilization policy expressed as like a
database filter so instead of just
saying can the user see this one thing
you say like what are all the things
this user can see i'm actually then
going to go make that as a database
query i'm going to the database handle
the heavy lifting of like filtering down
my you know what have 10 million records
down to the five the user can see
you know something that people often
overlook but it's to do that well
requires you to have a system that is
like aware that needs to be used in all
these like multiple different places
i was actually going to ask you some
stuff on filtering but maybe i can ask
that now
so specifically this because um you know
we talked about having authorization at
every layer i think this latency becomes
a big problem getting huge amounts of
data and then what do you present to to
the user right
what can also help with this you have
any sort of filtering specific tips and
tricks i don't know do you have a
filtering query language or something
like that so what we have
is
without wanting to go too much into the
weeds of this we sort of have an api
that allows you to say
instead of passing in a concrete object
and saying can the user see this you
basically just tell us like the type
the resource type you know the document
you pass in the you know arguments being
like user maybe the string read and this
type document and basically when also
goes and evaluates the authorization
logic you wrote in the policy it goes
through and basically instead of like
concretely checking you know is this
what are the fields on this resource it
kind of just like accumulates those as a
set of filters
and it can do this across like pretty
complex expressions right so
the
you know expression it gets back might
be
yes the user can see all documents
that belong to a folder
where the user has the admin role or the
member role on that folder
we do have like an internal
representation for that that does look
kind of very similar to at least in the
latest version looks quite similar to
like a relational algebra like a sql
kind of thing but it's mostly just like
an internal thing and then we basically
have an api that allows you to kind of
hook that up to your data models so that
typically is very easy to do with
something like an rm but we're also
making it possible to go like direct to
sql with that
the kind of core points is
yeah we sort of return this intermediate
expression that like kind of looks like
a data filter but we have like an api to
hook that up into
existing data models the idea being that
you
basically get to do this like rich
complex authorization and you know what
all the things i can see but your your
application data like stays exactly
where it is
and this is kind of
the big like conceptual difference
between
oso and like a zanzibar so what else
describing zanzibar as a developer
you're responsible for basically
migrating and moving all of your data
all your application data into the
central servers
it's very convenient to do that because
now it's like well now my data is
structured so i can do authorization for
you we kind of push ourselves
we challenge ourselves to say like
actually i think we don't have to deal
with migrating synchronizing data data
should stay where it is that's the
easiest way to be able to make like
dynamic up-to-date decisions so instead
we're going to do that work of like
figuring out how do we plug in and
integrate with your database
okay it's interesting so you also will
actually tie in with any of your data
models on your database and provide you
this query processing i guess that's
again something that you have to
actually look for okay that's great i
think i think and i guess there are many
examples on the documentation on how you
could do this right exactly yeah
what can be really nice about this as
well is
it also sometimes lets you do
like your data fetching and your
authorization in one shot it's because
like typically you're going to need to
you get the request you pass the
parameters you go and fetch some data
from the database we actually make it
possible to
in that one go fetch the data from the
database and apply the authorization
logic while you're doing it and so kind
of the
authorization overhead there is just the
kind of extra query parameters there is
no like separate latency piece needed
which is quite nice okay okay
interesting so
so you're saying that you know i mean
there could be i mean i think latency
will not be an issue if you tune the
parameters correctly
yeah
okay you've built this whole
authorization logic using your
declarative languages are called polar
and then you've got it implemented how
do you check if this is the right
behavior do you have any
testing framework that can check that
it's doing the right thing
yeah so typically
people just use the existing built-in
test frameworks in whatever language and
framework they're using the thing that's
particularly nice about it because what
the approach does is
decouples that logic from the
application code it's basically very
easy to unit test your logic because you
can just write a test that says create a
new dummy user make them an admin and
then check they can read a thing and if
that works you know the application
logic is going to work too because
they're using the same methods they're
using the same apis it basically makes
it very easy to kind of do that sort of
unit testing logic
it is something though that we want to
kind of work and develop on more is
actually
go beyond that and be able to let you
sort of do
kind of like property test style things
where you say
i want to check that any you know user
must have a role some role to be able to
access this kind of resource or
something we can just like just check
that over the policy itself as sort of a
step towards that like now we've
basically been adding a lot of sort of
validation checks to our policy right
now so you know we'll tell you if you've
tried to assign permissions to a role
doesn't exist or if there's a permission
that doesn't have any doesn't have any
roles assigned to it or you're missing a
piece of logic like we'll give you those
kind of built-in verification checks to
make sure you get it right
i should have asked you this in the
beginning but one of the things that is
plaguing
me to work and i i don't know if this is
a problem with a lot of people is that a
good rule of thumb on how many roles one
can have
there's a great question i'll say as few
as possible
as few as possible we spoke around like
very high level like what role-based
action control is but
i think the thing that's like really
important to do with roadway sectors
control is
it's effectively a way to communicate
to your end users like what they should
expect to be able to do inside an app
and
that's often pretty clear in like an
admin member worlds you know maybe like
admins can invite other users admin can
rename the organization they can delete
the organization and you know members
can typically use the app you know do
the things they need to roles work
really well when they communicate to an
end user like what their
responsibilities are inside an
application i think uh
gitlab the version control development
platform has like some really nice
examples of this where they have guests
they have like reviewers who can review
they have like moderators who can
moderate and update and maintainers who
can maintain the code it's you know
those names like they kind of tell you
what you should be able to do a mistake
people have to make is they just keep on
adding more and more roles to try and
address more and more different use
cases and like you end up with these
giant matrices of people trying to
figure out what they need
often the answer if you're finding that
you're trying to add more roles i
actually find often the answer can be
adding more
data model structures
so for example adding things like teams
or projects
because then like
users can they they kind of get a little
more control about themselves they can
create a sales team project or something
they can add a bunch of resources into
the sales team folder and they can give
you know the head of sales admin access
in just that folder and then that person
can't go and see like legal documents in
a different folder adding that is very
intuitive it's very natural for people
to understand that it's kind of an easy
way to go about it rather than try and
pre-empt those and build them as like a
bunch of roles yourself basically i do
know that there was this one project
that i was working on where they had so
many roles that when one person had to
onboard a new user they didn't know what
to do and they just went and gave them
system admin because
that was the one they could understand
yeah
anyway now that we've covered a few of
these things i want to get into a bit
onto the deployment and see consistency
part so now that you have this
authorization service so from what i
understood is you can have it embedded
into your application
as or you know have it outside but
what is the thing should it be a
separate service so that you can scale
it up and down and things like that or i
think it sort of depends we sort of have
like a bit of a golden rule also which
is
you should build authorization around
your application not the other way
around
so doing something like a zanzibar where
you
pull all of your data outside your
application or you refactor or migrate
your applications to use a specific
authorization system to me there's a
little bit of an answer pattern because
you're basically pushing so much of the
work onto the developers to understand
how to use the system how to synchronize
with it and things like that you know i
think there are ways you can kind of
mitigate less than that but generally
speaking i think
you should let like the shape of your
application drive how authorization
works
practically how we often see that
playing out is it's very very common for
people to have like a central
user management service where you know
users can get assigned to organizations
and roles within it and projects and
things like that because that's just
typically how like the application got
structured out you know and then there's
the individual applications are built
inside their own services and things
like that
those services need to get that roles
data to be able to make an authorization
decision
which
is kind of a form of centralization but
it's using the
the existing structure that is inherent
in your app you're saying okay well we
have we have a user management app
basically what do we need to do to make
it so that other applications can use
that for authorization decisions how do
we get the roles from that from that
service
and that basically allows you just to
keep the structure of your application
as it already was do you have the same
separation you already you know the
architect you were going with and
basically figuring out how to make that
work i think basically the
where the rubber meets the road of that
is
at certain scales that in itself does
become a challenging problem like it's
not just a oh whatever you just scale
that one app up and it does reach a
point where you do need like the
sophistication of something like of like
a zanzibar to really to make that
service have that low latency to have
that scale to be able to process that
much data the point is like you
identified that based on the size and
the scale of your application more so
than just like you do because of
authorization and like clearly google
reached that scale
i think there's been a few others airbnb
who've you know similarly reached that
scale like you know okay this is
becoming a huge part of a huge
bottleneck in application like we need
to like solve this problem to me that's
kind of the right way to approach it is
like you sort of
see where your application grows
naturally and like what shape it's
taking and once you see that that is a
bottleneck you look for the appropriate
technology to address it data plays a
big role in finding that out right
they'll face a huge part in it yeah
there are also these other authorization
services like i think ori is what i saw
which also seems to be built on zanzibar
i see a lot more how does also differ
from other services like this that you
see on open source platforms like github
the conceptual difference of where does
the data go where's the data live with
oso we
went to great length to let you keep the
data where it is and figure out how to
do authorization around your data
basically like using your data living
where it is a lot of some of the new
solutions coming through based on
zanzibar they they all work as a
separate service like you know r is no
different you need to put all your data
into the service that it can do do some
of this authorization stuff there's kind
of an interesting landscape of solutions
because there's been a long history of
existing authorization libraries that
tend to be for
specific frameworks like i think you
know rails has often had a pretty rich
history of like goods
authorization like libraries integrate
with rails they could do various pieces
of this
or
frameworks that very much focus on like
role-based access control but not much
else i think what we're seeing from
these from like oso and others is
really try and tackle the kind of
authorization complexity
like those skating problems that comes
with doing more complex models that
gives you more more granular control
more granular access control things like
that so i think that's like kind of the
the main trend we've seen from a lot of
these newer ones
in some ways we're kind of trying to
stick with the
tried and tested approach of keeping in
the app
versus kind of i think others which have
sort of seen google and being like well
maybe we should do what google does
i also tried one of the libraries that
you have supported on github so i tried
the node.js version i tried python
and then um i saw that you had no dotnet
support maybe you don't have so many
people programming in documents i just
wanted to ask you why is that we've had
so many requests for dotnet support
actually it's it's almost certainly like
the next one we'll get to the challenge
is
we did build and design oso so that it
could be like easily
a lot of the core of this is built in
rust and shared between the multiple
different libraries so that like you
know adding a library isn't you know
like a linear amount of work it's like
you know sublinear like small amount of
work at each library but i think what
we've been struggling with is we've been
kind of iterating a lot and making a ton
of improvements to the individual
libraries
that we've already sort of started
putting more efforts into like a few of
them
so in particular like node python and go
i think are getting a lot more attention
recently a lot of the newer stuff we're
trying out there first rather than
trying to do like six things
simultaneously if we did.net we know
that we wouldn't be able to like keep it
up to date at the the kind of the latest
and greatest oso version so we're sort
of waiting for some of the new features
to settle a little bit before expanding
out to other languages so that we
can kind of like release with sort of a
mature feature set um
so it's in the pipeline it is yeah
it's highly requested we have we have a
github issue to track it that's
i think is the most highly upvoted
if we're definitely aware of it yeah
finally i guess i had to ask you about
the choice of language that you've
written also and which is rust could you
just talk a little bit about it why did
you choose rust for writing also
one part is i just think rust is a real
pleasure and a real joy to develop in in
particular like the tooling around it
the developer experience around it is
fantastic like the error messages from
the compiler are very very useful and
they guide you in a good way there's got
a good linting system the package
management is very easy and things like
that so i just think it's a it's a joy
to program in from a more
technical perspective
the
advantages it offered aligned very
nicely is what we needed
so
you know number one we're building
something that's like on the critical
path for security so
you know being performant was important
you know protecting against memory
vulnerabilities was like a huge bonus
that it would offer
being able to write something that we
had like fine green control over that
was pretty low level like all that was
like very compelling benefits that it
would offer
and then the thing that sealed the deal
really was that we knew we wanted this
to be
something weird in bed in multiple
languages
the most natural way for us to do that
would be to have some kind of a c
apic interface as soon as you need that
that really limits your options down to
a few different things and felt like
kind of rust was like the best of the
bunch for doing that one other thing as
well was
which is very convenient nice from like
the runtime models
because this kind of just compiles down
to effectually like a system library
it's kind of how it basically looks
under the surface there are no like
background threads there's no runtime
there's no extra processing deadlocks
happening like none of that stuff's
happening under the surface it's like
oso only executes when you told it to do
something and if you're doing something
it does nothing it's just it's
it's not blocking or consuming resources
or there's no garbage collection or
anything like that
it's just very very very predictable you
kind of know what it's going to do
you're not going to see
bizarre like latency spikes and things
like that
okay
interesting i think so that's on one of
my bucket list
this has been great before i let you go
slam i just wanted to ask you one final
question so to sum this whole
conversation up are there any like some
three golden rules that you would say
for
building a consistent
authorization system or service
the number one
rule of authorization is
your ability for your end users
first and foremost like
that is kind of why i love this area as
well it's like
i think the end user experience should
be what drives a lot of the decision
making here like what is ultimately
building products that's kind of the
main thing that matters and so
that i think just kind of leads you to
think around like what's gonna make
sense the user is it about roles is it
relationships like how how do you
explain this to a user and i think
basically models help you have like a
consistent version of that on the back
end we spoke about like architecturally
you know building authorization around
your application not the other way
around
to me that means primarily you know
leaving the application data where it is
being able to
reuse or repurpose what you already have
so you're not you're duplicating effort
your application is already capable of
fetching things from the database your
application already has a way to
determine if somebody belongs an
organization has a data model that says
that how do you make sure you can reuse
that inside one app or across like
multiple applications you know how are
we distributing data across our
architecture that's how authorization
should be distributed
i think number three is
something we haven't touched on yet but
such a huge part of this is the
developer experience as well you know
authorization is an interesting one it's
that like you know at a bigger team
you're gonna want you're gonna want your
security engineers like helping out
helping audit your code check that it's
all correct but ultimately like
authorization is so intuitive in the
application that you're going to want
that developer experience to be good and
such a core part of it
and so that means you know providing
them something that's easy for them to
work with it's easy for them to update
and modify one that comes up a lot it's
like if a
developer is adding a new feature
you know they add a new endpoint and
they need to be able to check you know
make sure they add a new permission that
the user can do this thing or not you
want that to be like
instinctive and intuitive to them you
want them to be able to test that
locally to figure it out to kind of get
that working you don't want it to be
like they send some
pr off into the void where it gets like
reviewed by some person three weeks
later and comes back to them and
or like
you know if the permissions break in
production that they don't know why like
it's a really crucial thing to get right
and it it forces you a little bit to
reevaluate how you think around
like who owns the authorization code
basically
i think what goes hand-in-hand with that
hand in hand with that actually comes
back to the first point just you know
developers the ones building they have
the the context of the product they're
the ones building the product features
they hopefully are geared in on what the
users want and so like empowering them
to be able to make good authorization
decisions kind of like connects that
full circle you know
that's great things very well put
together so thank you so much for coming
on the show thank you for having me this
is fun this is uh signing off for
priyanka raghavan for software
engineering video thanks
thanks for listening to sc radio an
educational program brought to you by
ieee software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at se radio.net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on linkedin facebook twitter or through
our slack channel at scradio.slack.com
you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net this and all other episodes
of sc radio is licensed under creative
commons license 2.5
thanks for listening